[
  {
    "question": "Pollen grains are generally ______ measuring about 25-50 micrometers in diameter.",
    "answer": "spherical"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pollen grains have a prominent ______-layered wall.",
    "answer": "two"
  },
  {
    "question": "The hard outer layer of pollen grain is called the ______.",
    "answer": "exine"
  },
  {
    "question": "The exine is made up of ______.",
    "answer": "sporopollenin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sporopollenin is one of the most ______ organic material known.",
    "answer": "resistant"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sporopollenin can withstand high temperatures and strong ______ and alkali.",
    "answer": "acids"
  },
  {
    "question": "No enzyme that degrades ______ is so far known.",
    "answer": "sporopollenin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pollen grain exine has prominent apertures called ______.",
    "answer": "germ pores"
  },
  {
    "question": "In germ pores, ______ is absent.",
    "answer": "sporopollenin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pollen grains are well-preserved as ______ because of the presence of sporopollenin.",
    "answer": "fossils"
  },
  {
    "question": "The inner wall of the pollen grain is called the ______.",
    "answer": "intine"
  },
  {
    "question": "The intine is a thin and continuous layer made up of cellulose and ______.",
    "answer": "pectin"
  },
  {
    "question": "The cytoplasm of pollen grain is surrounded by a ______ membrane.",
    "answer": "plasma"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the pollen grain is mature it contains two cells, the ______ cell and generative cell.",
    "answer": "vegetative"
  },
  {
    "question": "The vegetative cell is bigger, has abundant food reserve and a large irregularly shaped ______.",
    "answer": "nucleus"
  },
  {
    "question": "The generative cell is small and floats in the cytoplasm of the ______ cell.",
    "answer": "vegetative"
  },
  {
    "question": "The generative cell is spindle shaped with dense cytoplasm and a ______.",
    "answer": "nucleus"
  },
  {
    "question": "In over ______ per cent of angiosperms, pollen grains are shed at this 2-celled stage.",
    "answer": "60"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the remaining species, the generative cell divides ______ to give rise to the two male gametes.",
    "answer": "mitotically"
  },
  {
    "question": "Pollen grains of many species cause severe allergies and ______ afflictions.",
    "answer": "bronchial"
  },
  {
    "question": "Parthenium or carrot grass came into India as a contaminant with imported ______.",
    "answer": "wheat"
  },
  {
    "question": "Parthenium has become ubiquitous in occurrence and causes pollen ______.",
    "answer": "allergy"
  }
    ]
